Frieren,
芙莉蓮
find Aureole and talk to Himmel.
去找靈魂長眠之地 然後跟欣梅爾好好聊一聊吧
In the northernmost point of the continent,
在大陸極北之境
I reached Aureole, the land where souls rest,
我抵達了靈魂安息的所在 靈魂長眠之地
a place which the people of this world call heaven.
這個世界的人稱那裡為天國
There were many souls gathered there
在那裡聚集了眾多靈魂
and I talked to my former comrades.
我與昔日戰友進行了對話
Sorry,
不好意思了
it will be a long journey.
這趟旅途會很漫長
It took us ten years.
我們一行人花了整整十年
I see…
這樣啊
It's the same journey all of you took to the Demon King's castle.
接下來要走的是和欣梅爾大人你們 前往魔王城時相同的道路啊
That's right.
沒錯
It was a mere ten-year adventure.
只是十年的冒險而已
"One-hundredth," huh?
“百分之一”嗎？
Frieren, you're not staying in the royal capital?
芙莉蓮，妳不打算留在王都嗎？
I'll continue traveling.
我會繼續旅行
-On your own? -It's easier that way.
-自己一個人？ -這樣更輕鬆啊
You're not going to take an apprentice?
妳不打算收個徒弟嗎？
It's better to have someone to talk to when traveling.
旅途中有個人能聊聊天會更好
It's a waste of time.
那只會浪費時間
Even if I teach them things, they die right away.
就算教他們東西，他們也很快就死了
Frieren, that's not what interacting with people is about.
芙莉蓮 人跟人之間的互動不是那樣子的
It is. My adventures with all of you
是那樣沒錯，跟你們一同冒險的時光
don't even make up one-hundredth of my life.
都還佔不到我人生中的百分之一
I vaguely remember saying something like that.
我隱約記得說過那種話呢
Isn't it funny?
不是很有趣嗎？
What?
哪裡有趣？
That one-hundredth
那不到百分之一的時光
changed you.
改變了妳
All right, see you.
那就再見了
Yeah, see you.
嗯，再見
For me, it's half of my life.
對我來說，十年是我一半的人生呢
That's how much time I've spent with you.
我跟您渡過的時光 就佔了我人生的一半
It'll just keep getting longer from here on.
以後還會更多的
ORIGINAL STORY BY KANEHITO YAMADA / TSUKASA ABE
（原作：山田鐘人，作畫：阿部司）
Now listen, Fern.
聽好了，費倫
From now on, listen to what Frieren says
從今以後要好好聽芙莉蓮的話
and be a good girl.
做個乖孩子喔
Or else…
否則的話…
Or else?
否則的話？
I'll become a ghost and haunt you.
死了之後，我會變成鬼魂來找妳喔
Master Heiter, so if I'm a bad girl,
海塔大人，所以如果我當個壞孩子
does that mean I get to see you again?
就表示我可以再見到您嗎？
You've become so devious.
妳變狡猾了呢
Who did you take after?
到底是像到誰？
I take that back.
收回前言
If you are a good girl,
如果妳當個乖孩子
maybe I will come to haunt you just a little.
也許我會偶爾回來看看妳
Apparently, we're almost at the village.
我們差不多要到村子了
I see.
是嗎？
-What? -Nothing.
-怎麼了？ -沒什麼
28 YEARS FROM THE DEATH OF HIMMEL THE HERO
（勇者欣梅爾逝世的28年後）
WILLE REGION IN THE CENTRAL LANDS
（中央諸國，威雷地區）
You want to cross the mountain pass, don't you?
妳們想要穿過山道吧？
I advise you not to.
我勸妳們還是別去了
Many people have gone missing already.
已經有很多人失蹤了
Is there a monster?
有魔物嗎？
People say they were taken away by ghosts.
聽說是被幽靈給帶走了
There are even eyewitnesses.
有人親眼看到過
I wonder if they're the undead.
難道是活死人？
Do you know what those ghosts looked like?
妳知道那些幽靈長什麼樣子嗎？
I don't know that much.
那個我就不清楚了
If you're curious, why don't you ask the eyewitnesses?
如果妳們想知道的話 要不要直接去問看過的人呢？
If you summarize it up,
總結大家的話來說
people have witnessed ghosts of their family and friends
人們親眼看到已故親友的幽靈
and they looked just like they did before they died.
看起來就跟生前一模一樣
Some people said the ghosts talked to them.
有些人還說幽靈對他們開口說話
This is not the work of the undead.
那就不是活死人所為了
Really?
是這樣嗎？
"Undead" is a collective term referring to corpses controlled by magic.
“活死人”是用來 統稱遭魔法操縱的屍體
Like zombies and skeletons.
比如殭屍跟骷髏這類的
But in this case, they looked like how they did before they died.
但這個情形是看起來跟生前一模一樣
A corpse wouldn't look like that.
屍體的話是無法辦到這點的
This is a completely different kind of monster.
這完全是不同的魔物所為
You seem to know what it is.
您看來已經知道是哪種魔物了
It has a twisted personality so let's try not to run into it.
那傢伙人格很扭曲 我們要小心別遇上了
We'll leave first thing in the morning.
明天一早就離開村子吧
Mistress Frieren, the villagers are in need of help.
芙莉蓮大人，村裡的人需要幫忙
That's something Himmel and the crew would say.
欣梅爾跟其他人也會這麼說呢
Because I am a good girl, unlike you, Mistress Frieren.
畢竟我跟芙莉蓮大人不一樣 我可是個乖孩子呢
Well, if you're up for it, I guess it's fine.
好吧，如果妳想的話，那就這麼做吧
We have to cross the mountain pass anyway.
反正我們也必須穿過山道
This is where a villager went missing recently.
這裡就是近來村民消失的地方吧
Are there any clues…
線索的話…
There's more than enough.
要多少有多少呢
There are traces of magic that was used here.
這裡有使用過魔法的痕跡
Yeah. What kind of magic do you think it was?
說得沒錯，妳覺得是哪種魔法？
Illusion magic.
是幻影魔法
There are monsters who lure their prey by using illusions.
有的魔物會用幻覺來吸引獵物
That's what I read in the book on the ecology of magic.
我在魔法生態學的書上讀到的
Einsam.
幻影鬼
Even among those types of monsters, they are especially cunning, greedy,
是所有魔物類型中 最狡猾貪婪的一種
and picky eaters who only feed on humans.
而且很偏食，只捕食人類
They lure you in with illusions of the dead.
他們用死者的幻影誘惑人
People get lured in by something like that?
人們會被那種東西蠱惑嗎？
They show you illusions of people who were dear to you.
你看到的會是珍愛之人的幻影
But the illusions that Einsam uses are non-threatening to mages.
但幻影鬼製造的幻影 對魔法使不具威脅性
They easily disperse when they're hit with highly concentrated mana
只要用攻擊魔法 那種高密度魔力攻擊那些幻影
like offensive magic.
很容易就會消散
So you just have to shoot down the illusions.
所以只要擊倒幻影就可以了吧
Can you shoot?
妳動得了手嗎？
Of course. After all, I know they aren't real.
當然，畢竟我清楚他們不是真的
I shot down an illusion of my master as she begged for her life.
我曾經擊倒的幻影 是苦苦求我饒她一命的師父
But then again, I was used to hearing her beg for her life,
不過我當時已經習慣師父向我求饒了
so it didn't hurt my conscience that much.
所以我並不會有罪惡感
Even still, it's not the greatest feeling.
儘管如此，那種感覺仍不好受
What do you mean, you were used to hearing her beg for her life?
習慣師父求饒是什麼意思啊？
It's getting foggy.
起霧了
It's close.
很靠近了
When the illusions appear, don't hesitate to shoot.
出現幻影的時候，別猶豫，直接動手
Fern.
費倫
There it is.
出現了
This is the "illusion of the dead."
這就是“死者的幻影”
I'm calm.
我很冷靜
I can shoot it.
我可以做到
You're looking like a real mage now.
看來妳成為像樣的魔法使了
Because you were a good girl,
因為妳是個乖孩子
I decided to haunt you a little bit.
所以我決定偶爾回來看看妳
It's my memory.
這是我的回憶
It was a good thing you chose to become a mage.
當初決定成為魔法使是正確的選擇呢
You've always loved magic…
妳一直都很喜歡魔法…
He's using my memories.
這傢伙在利用我的回憶
How cruel.
好殘酷
These are my precious memories.
這可是我寶貴的回憶啊
Fern.
費倫
She can't, huh?
做不到嗎？
They chose Himmel, huh?
這回變成了欣梅爾啊？
I assumed that it would be my master again.
我還以為又會是師父呢
Does this mean that I've changed at least a little?
這表示我或多或少有些變了吧？
Frieren, shoot me.
芙莉蓮，動手
Yes, that's something Himmel would say.
沒錯，欣梅爾一定會這麼說的
This mountain pass is safe now.
現在這樣山道就安全了吧
Mistress Frieren,
芙莉蓮大人
that was an illusion of Master Heiter.
剛剛的幻影是海塔大人
-He was fake. -That's right.
-是假貨 -沒錯
Now, let's go see the real one.
現在去看真貨吧
After all, we're heading to Aureole.
畢竟我們是要去靈魂長眠之地嘛
You're right.
說得也是
28 YEARS FROM THE DEATH OF HIMMEL THE HERO
（勇者欣梅爾逝世的28年後）
RIEGEL CANYON IN THE CENTRAL LANDS
（中央諸國，里格爾峽谷）
That's a dragon?
那是龍嗎？
It's my first time seeing one.
我還是第一次看到
Look at the nest.
妳看牠的巢
Do you see that grimoire?
看到那本魔導書沒？
I've been looking for that one.
我一直在找那本
As usual, you love those things.
您還真是喜歡這些東西呢
But why is it there?
不過那本書為什麼會在那裡？
Dragons use items imbued with mana to build their nests.
因為龍喜歡用具有魔力的材料築巢啊
The solar dragon.
紅鏡龍
This one has devoured many adventurers.
牠已經吃掉好幾個冒險者了
Either way, it'd be good to kill it.
不管怎麼樣都得解決牠
-Be careful not to hit the nest. -Yes.
-小心不要打到巢 -好
Mistress Frieren,
芙莉蓮大人
it didn't do much.
沒什麼效果耶
Dragons are so hard.
龍果然就是硬
We have no choice. Let's run!
沒辦法了，跑吧！
We finally got rid of it.
總算擺脫牠了
It flies so fast.
牠飛得好快
We probably can't fight it in the air either.
看來空中戰也打不過呢
I… I thought I was going to die.
我…我還以為死定了
Let's go back now.
那回去吧
If we keep doing this, we'll eventually take it down.
持續打下去的話，總有一天會打贏的
Right…
也對啦…
Playing tag with a dragon is not something a mage should do.
跟龍玩鬼抓人 實在不是身為魔法使應該做的事
I guess I'll have to welcome another member.
還是好好再找個同伴吧
A vanguard?
前衛？
Yeah, you're looking for one, right?
對，妳不是在找嗎？
In a village along the Riegel Canyon,
在里格爾峽谷旁的村子裡
there's a warrior named Stark.
有個名叫修塔爾克的戰士
When you enter the northern lands, pick him up while you're at it.
要去北方諸國時，順便帶他走吧
He's my apprentice.
他是我的徒弟
He's a good warrior?
他是個優秀的戰士嗎？
I can't believe it's so peaceful here with a dragon nearby.
話說回來，村裡這麼平靜 一點也不像附近有隻龍呢
I agree.
說得是呢
Mistress Frieren,
芙莉蓮大人
what kind of magic is recorded in that grimoire?
那本魔導書裡面記載了哪種魔法啊？
A spell that lets you see through clothes.
讓衣服看起來變透明的魔法
You really only collect weird spells, don't you.
您總是收集奇怪的魔法呢
It's my hobby after all.
畢竟是我的嗜好啊
But it can be useful.
但這個也能很實用喔
Depending on what you consider "clothes,"
要看妳對“衣服”的定義是什麼
-you can check for weapons-- -Excuse me.
-也可以暗中查看對方的武器… -打擾一下
May I have a moment of your time?
能借一步說話嗎？
Master Stark wants to meet you.
修塔爾克大人想要見見兩位
I guess we don't have to look for him.
看來不用另外費工夫找他了呢
About three years ago,
大概三年前左右
that dragon attacked our village.
那隻龍襲擊了我們村子
That is when Master Stark appeared.
修塔爾克大人就是那時候出現的
Even when he was face-to-face with the dragon, he did not budge an inch.
儘管跟龍正面交鋒，他卻毫不退縮
After a very long staredown,
他們互相凝視許久之後
the dragon went away.
那條龍就飛走了
Ever since then, thanks to the fact that he stays here,
自那之後，幸虧他留在了這裡
we are able to live peacefully
我們才得以平靜度日
without being attacked by the dragon.
不受龍的侵襲
Then if we can get Master Stark to help us,
這樣的話 可以拜託修塔爾克大人幫忙
we can take the dragon down.
我們就能打倒龍了
I hope so.
但願如此
Can I become a strong warrior like you, Stark?
我可以成為像修塔爾克一樣 強大的戰士嗎？
You can.
當然可以
But warriors aren't all that great.
但是戰士可沒你們想的那麼好喔
Oh, Grandma!
喔，婆婆！
You two were messing with the dragon?
是妳們去招惹那條龍的？
Don't agitate it too much. It'll put the village in danger.
不要老是刺激牠 這樣會給村子招來危險
Dragons are more terrifying than you think.
龍遠比妳們想像的更可怕
This scar on my forehead is from when I fought
我額頭上這個傷就是
-a shadow dragon-- -That scar is not that special.
-跟暗黑龍戰鬥… -也不是什麼大不了的傷吧
Were you sent by my master? Who are you?
是我師父派妳們來的嗎？ 妳是什麼人？
Frieren the mage.
魔法使芙莉蓮
Grandma, can you give us a moment alone?
婆婆，可以請妳迴避一下嗎？
Don't worry. They're friends of my master.
沒事的，她們是我師父的熟人
Master was mad, wasn't he?
師父很生氣吧？
Since I left without saying anything.
因為我什麼都沒說就離開了
Stark, why haven't you taken down the dragon?
修塔爾克，你為什麼不把龍殲滅呢？
There's no reason for you to stay in this village.
你沒有留在這個村子的理由吧
Can you tell me what you want first?
妳們能先說說這趟來訪的目的嗎？
If you want me to go back to my master, I'm not going to.
如果是要我回師父身邊的話 那我只能說抱歉了
We want you to join us as a vanguard.
我們希望你能以前衛的身分加入我們
But first, we want you to help us take down the solar dragon.
首先，先幫我們打倒紅鏡龍吧
I want the grimoire that's in its nest.
我想要牠巢中的那本魔導書
-Why? -It's just my hobby.
-為什麼？ -純粹興趣使然
There's no special reason.
沒什麼特別的理由
This is a solar dragon we're talking about.
對方可是紅鏡龍
It's not something you fight for no reason.
誰會沒來由地去找牠打架啊？
Amazing!
好厲害！
Well…
說得也是…
There were idiots who praised me for the spells I collected.
以前有過幾個笨蛋 會因為我收集的魔法而誇我
I guess that's my reason.
我想那就是原因吧
Praised you, huh?
誇妳嗎？
-What a silly reason. -Right?
-真是無聊的理由 -是吧？
I don't mind joining you.
要我加入妳們也無所謂
Master told you to take me along, right?
是師父要妳們帶我一起走的吧？
But you will have to take down the solar dragon no matter what.
但無論如何，必須先打倒紅鏡龍
Honestly, I can't do it alone.
老實說，光靠我一個是辦不到的
Frieren, you can take it down, right?
芙莉蓮，妳可以打倒牠的吧？
Most definitely, as long as you can distract it for 30 seconds.
只要你能讓牠分心三十秒 我就有把握
I see.
原來如此
For 30 seconds, huh?
三十秒嗎？
Do I have to be in charge of that?
我是不是一定要出手才行？
What is this man talking about?
這傢伙在說什麼啊？
I knew it.
果然是這樣
Stark, how many monsters have you fought?
修塔爾克 你有跟魔物戰鬥的經驗嗎？
Zero!
完全沒有！
Help me, Frieren!
幫幫我，芙莉蓮！
I actually tried to stand up against it at first!
我一開始也有好好面對巨龍啊！
But I was so scared that I couldn't move an inch.
但是我實在太害怕了 所以動也不敢動
It slices through houses
那傢伙切房子
like they're vegetables!
就跟切菜一樣啊！
Humans are not meant to fight such a thing!
人類根本不可能是牠的對手！
But when the dragon spared my life on a whim…
那條龍一時興起饒了我一命…
For some reason
後來不知道為什麼
the dragon stopped attacking the village and I became a hero.
牠就再也沒有攻擊過村子 我也自此成為了英雄
The villagers are such nice people!
村民們人都超級好！
You're still young, so you need to eat up!
你還這麼年輕，要多吃一點！
Stark, show me your new move!
修塔爾克，讓我見識你的新招式！
I can't run away from this situation anymore!
事情變成這樣，我根本逃不了！
Mistress Frieren, he is no good.
芙莉蓮大人，這傢伙沒救了
Let's find someone else.
我們去找別人吧
Don't leave me!
不要丟下我啊！
No, he can fight the dragon.
不，他可以跟龍戰鬥
I know he can.
我知道他可以
You sound like a doting parent.
您聽起來好像溺愛孩子的父母
Stark, I will give you one night.
修塔爾克，我給你一個晚上
Think about it.
你好好考慮
You know you can't keep this up forever.
你知道這樣下去不是辦法吧？
I heard you met Master Stark.
聽說妳們見過修塔爾克大人了
Wasn't he a nice boy?
是個不錯的年輕人吧？
He always eats at our place,
他來我們家吃飯的時候
like it's the most delicious food ever.
總是吃得津津有味
Master Stark is loved by the people.
修塔爾克大人受到很多人喜愛呢
Well, it does seem like he is a kind person.
也是啊，那傢伙看上去是個溫柔的人
Kind?
溫柔？
All I saw was a coward.
我只看到一個膽小鬼而已
I don't disagree that he is a coward.
我不否認他很膽小
Remember when you fought a monster for the first time, even you…
妳自己第一次 跟魔物戰鬥的時候不也是…
Fine, I'll forget about that.
好，我會忘掉這件事的
Jeez…
真是的
When you were small, you used to be so innocent and cute.
妳小時候明明既單純又可愛的
By the way, why doesn't the dragon attack this village?
話說回來 那隻龍為什麼不攻擊這個村子呢？
I don't know. Maybe it's just not in the mood
不清楚，也許牠沒那個興致吧
or…
或是…
What's that sound?
那是什麼聲音？
It must be Stark.
一定是修塔爾克
If you're curious, go and see.
好奇的話就去看看啊
I'm going to sleep.
我要去睡了
He's a good warrior?
他是個優秀的戰士嗎？
In the past,
以前
when his hometown was attacked by demons,
他的家鄉遭到魔物攻擊
he ran away by himself like the coward he is.
因為很膽小，他獨自逃跑了
Just like me.
就跟我一樣
That's why I taught him everything I know.
所以我才對他傾囊相授
Now, he has become someone who can fight for others.
他現在是可以為他人而戰的戰士了
I see. He is a good warrior then.
這樣啊，那他就是個優秀的戰士了
So this was the aftermath of his training, huh?
原來這是他修行造成的痕跡
-Time waits for no one. -That old hag.
-時間不等人 -臭老太婆嗎？
Isn't that dangerous?
那不是很危險嗎？
Do not cause
不要給村裡
-any trouble in this town. -He was disappointed in me.
-帶來麻煩 -他對我很失望
Your hands are trembling.
你的手在發抖
You even tremble the same way.
連發抖的方式也一樣呢
"The Hero of the Village."
村子的英雄
Subtitle translation by: Kiko Morita
字幕翻譯：洪貞韻